<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <id>https://scvi-tools.org/blog</id>
    <title>scvi-tools Blog</title>
    <updated>2021-03-03T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
    <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://scvi-tools.org/blog"/>
    <subtitle>scvi-tools Blog</subtitle>
    <icon>https://scvi-tools.org/img/favicon.ico</icon>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[scvi-tools 0.9.0 release]]></title>
        <id>v090</id>
        <link href="https://scvi-tools.org/blog/v090"/>
        <updated>2021-03-03T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Today we officially released scvi-tools version 0.9.0 (changelog). This release marks the culmination of five months of work on the backend of the codebase, which came after three months of work on the frontend.]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Adam Gayoso, Romain Lopez, Galen Xing, Nir Yosef</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hyperparameter search for scVI]]></title>
        <id>autotune</id>
        <link href="https://scvi-tools.org/blog/autotune"/>
        <updated>2019-07-05T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[A study of the effects of hyperparameter optimization on scVI models.]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Gabriel Misrachi, Jeffrey Regier, Romain Lopez, Nir Yosef</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Should we zero-inflate scVI?]]></title>
        <id>zero-inflation</id>
        <link href="https://scvi-tools.org/blog/zero-inflation"/>
        <updated>2019-06-25T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Droplet- based single-cell RNA sequencing (scRNA-seq) datasets typically contain at least 90% zero entries. How can we best model these zeros? Recent work focused on modeling zeros with a mixture of count distributions. The first component is meant to reflect whether such an entry can be explained solely by the limited amount of sampling (on average ~5% or less of the molecules in the cell). The second component is generally used to reflect "surprising" zeros caused by measurement bias, transient transcriptional noise (e.g., "bursty" gene with a short mRNA half life), or true longer-term heterogeneity that can not be captured by a similified (low dimensional) representation of the data. Among others, zero-inflated distributions (i.e., zero-inflated negative binomial) have been widely adopted to model gene expression levels (1, 2).]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Oscar Clivio, Pierre Boyeau, Romain Lopez, Jeffrey Regier, Nir Yosef</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
</feed>