<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <id>https://scvi-tools.org/blog</id>
    <title>scvi-tools Blog</title>
    <updated>2025-07-03T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
    <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://scvi-tools.org/blog"/>
    <subtitle>scvi-tools Blog</subtitle>
    <icon>https://scvi-tools.org/img/favicon.ico</icon>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[scvi-tools 1.3 release]]></title>
        <id>v13</id>
        <link href="https://scvi-tools.org/blog/v13"/>
        <updated>2025-07-03T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Introduction]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Ori Kronfeld</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Mini-batch size in destVI]]></title>
        <id>destvi-batchsize</id>
        <link href="https://scvi-tools.org/blog/destvi-batchsize"/>
        <updated>2022-05-29T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[The task of deconvolution of spot-based spatial transcriptomics (ST) data consists in finding the cellular composition in spots of ST assays. Indeed, by design each spot consists of several individual cells. Our lab developed destVI as a tool to study cell type composition of spots (1). In the case where one expects within cell type variation (i.e., activation states), DestVI was designed to infer the activation state of individual cell types in each spot and therefore gives additional resolution of cell composition over competing algorithms. In our own benchmarking of destVI, we found comparable performance in prediction of cell type proportions to other state of the art algorithms like Cell2Location (2). A recent benchmarking study compared the performance of several gene imputation as well as deconvolution methods. Given the ever increasing number of deconvolution methods, the effort to benchmark those tools on a variety of simulated data is timely (3). In two of the benchmarking cases, DestVI had the worst performance. Along with the recent acceptance of the manuscript, we published several fixes to the codebase in scvi-tools v0.16.0, repeated those experiments and analyzed the reasons for failure of spot deconvolution in the given experiments. Briefly, we show that the poor performance was due to the mini-batch size used during optimization, and resolving this help recovering competitive accuracy. Additionally, we provide the user with a heuristic for future use.]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Can Ergen, Romain Lopez, Nir Yosef</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[scvi-tools 0.9.0 release]]></title>
        <id>v090</id>
        <link href="https://scvi-tools.org/blog/v090"/>
        <updated>2021-03-03T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Today we officially released scvi-tools version 0.9.0 (changelog). This release marks the culmination of five months of work on the backend of the codebase, which came after three months of work on the frontend.]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Adam Gayoso, Romain Lopez, Galen Xing, Nir Yosef</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hyperparameter search for scVI]]></title>
        <id>autotune</id>
        <link href="https://scvi-tools.org/blog/autotune"/>
        <updated>2019-07-05T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[A study of the effects of hyperparameter optimization on scVI models.]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Gabriel Misrachi, Jeffrey Regier, Romain Lopez, Nir Yosef</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Should we zero-inflate scVI?]]></title>
        <id>zero-inflation</id>
        <link href="https://scvi-tools.org/blog/zero-inflation"/>
        <updated>2019-06-25T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Droplet- based single-cell RNA sequencing (scRNA-seq) datasets typically contain at least 90% zero entries. How can we best model these zeros? Recent work focused on modeling zeros with a mixture of count distributions. The first component is meant to reflect whether such an entry can be explained solely by the limited amount of sampling (on average ~5% or less of the molecules in the cell). The second component is generally used to reflect "surprising" zeros caused by measurement bias, transient transcriptional noise (e.g., "bursty" gene with a short mRNA half life), or true longer-term heterogeneity that can not be captured by a similified (low dimensional) representation of the data. Among others, zero-inflated distributions (i.e., zero-inflated negative binomial) have been widely adopted to model gene expression levels (1, 2).]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Oscar Clivio, Pierre Boyeau, Romain Lopez, Jeffrey Regier, Nir Yosef</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
</feed>